Rockefeller Institute Meningitis Records 1907-1913 Mss.Ms.Coll.34
American Philosophical Society
Rockefeller Institute. Meningitis Records
1907-1913
Mss.Ms.Coll.34
American Philosophical Society
8.0 Linear feet
In 1892, the physician and medical administrator Simon Flexner began research on cerebrospinal meningitis, a meningococcal disease with an untreated mortality rate between 70 and 90%. Experimenting on monkeys, Flexner developed a promising serum treatment for the disease by 1903, which he used extensively during the epidemic outbreaks of meningitis in New York City in 1904-1905 and 1907. For several years, Flexner kept his serum under his close supervision, with the result that the Rockefeller Institute became the primary source for knowledge about meningitis and its treatment. The 8 linear feet of Records amassed at the Rockefeller Institute between 1907 and 1913 document Simon Flexner's deployment of his serum treatment for cerebrospinal meningitis and his on-going interest in the epidemiology, etiology, and treatment of the disease. The collection consists largely of patient records, with data on hospitals and physicians to whom Flexner has dispensed his serum.
Rockefeller Institute.
Bibliography
Flexner, Simon and James W. Jobling, "An analysis of four hundred cases of epidemic meningitis treated with the anti-meningitis serum," Journal of Experimental Medicine 10, 5 (1908): 690-733.
Related Archival Materials note
The Simon Flexner Papers contains a quantity of additional information on meningitis, usually listed under the names of individual physicians and scientists interested in polio research.
The Library also houses a collection of epidemiological and other records accumulated by the Rockefeller Institute during the poliomyelitis epidemic of 1916 (Ms. Coll. 33).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the Rockefeller Institute, 1964.
Scope and Contents note
The 8 linear feet of Records amassed at the Rockefeller Institute between 1907 and 1913 document Simon Flexner's deployment of his serum treatment for cerebrospinal meningitis and his on-going interest in the epidemiology, etiology, and treatment of the disease. The collection consists largely of patient records, with data on hospitals and physicians to whom Flexner has dispensed his serum.
Biographical/Historical note
In 1892, the physician and medical administrator Simon Flexner began research on cerebrospinal meningitis, a meningococcal disease with an untreated mortality rate between 70 and 90%. Experimenting on monkeys, Flexner developed a promising serum treatment for the disease by 1903, which he used extensively during the epidemic outbreaks of meningitis in New York City in 1904-1905 and 1907. For several years, Flexner kept his serum under his close supervision, with the result that the Rockefeller Institute became the primary source for knowledge about meningitis and its treatment.
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946; Epidemics; Epidemiology; Medical records; Meningitis; Serum
- Rockefeller Institute Meningitis Records, 1907-1913; 8 lin. feet
  - Serum listing, 1907-1910; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - Serum listing, 1907-1910; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - Serum testing: a. Analysis of 1,300 case; b. tabulation of cases; c. Old meningitis reports, ca.1908; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 2)
  - Serum testing, 1907-1910; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 3)
  - Serum testing, 1907-1911; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 4)
  - Serum testing, 1907-1911; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 5)
  - Serum testing, 1907-1911; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 6)
  - Serum testing, 1908-1911; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 7)
  - Serum testing, 1908-1911; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 8)
  - Serum testing, 1908-1910; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 9)
  - Serum testing, 1907-1909; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 10)
  - Serum testing, 1907-1913; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 11)
  - Serum testing; history and miscellaneous, 1909-1911; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 12)
  - Card file index of hospitals and doctors supplied with serum, ca.1907-1913; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 13)
  - Card file, ca.1907-1910; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 14)
  - Card file, ca.1907-1910; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 15)
  - Card file, ca.1907-1910; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 16)